A Guide to the Norris Family Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Norris Family Papers 1661-1942
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2454, 2454-a, 2562
This collection consists of ca. 600 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The original Jefferson Davis Norris collection was given to the University by Dudley Page Cotton and Miss Martha Norris of Medomak, Maine, in July, 1946, which Mrs. Cotton subsequently expanded with additional materials received 30 May 1952 (2454-a), and to which Mrs. Cotton added the papers of William Norris (2562) on 3 December 1946. The letter of 1880 February 20 from Jefferson Davis to William Norris remains the property of Mrs. Dudley Page Cotton, Jr., and Mr. Jefferson Cabell Cotton.
Scope and Content Information
The Norris Family Papers, 1661-1942, have been divided into four major sections, the papers of Colonial William Norris, the papers of Jefferson Davis Norris, the papers of members of J. D. Norris' immediate family, and the papers of other families that are distantly related to the Norrises.
The papers, 1857-1896, of William Norris, Colonel in the Signal Corps of the Confederate Army, contain primarily business letters and invitations. An 1880 letter from Col. Norris to Jefferson Davis and Davis' reply have been placed in a separate folder. The rest of Col. Norris' correspondence has been arranged chronologically. There is also a scrapbook containing newspaper clippings on miscellaneous topics.
The papers, 1880-1942, of Jefferson Davis Norris, a Maryland lawyer who received his degree in 1890 from the University of Virginia are further broken down into four sub-divisions. First, there is the correspondence of J. D. Norris with various members of his immediate family which has been arranged genealogically as follows: correspondence with his father, Col. William Norris, with his mother, Ellen Norris; with his brother, William Catesby Norris; with his sisters, Sarita M. and Susan F. Norris; with his wife Cabell Norris; and with his daughters, Josephine and Martha Jefferson "Bee" Norris. Correspondence with his mother and with his brother contain colorful descriptions of life at the University of Virginia in the 1890s. Personal correspondence with various friends follows his family correspondence. Where the quantity of correspondence has warranted it, individual correspondence has also been broken down by decade and runs chronologically.
The second sub-section of J. D. Norris' papers consists of his business correspondence. This is arranged chronologically by decade with certain correspondence pulled and placed in separate folders because of its quantity or because of its topical interest. Norris' business letters during the thirties in particular indicate the troubles and turmoils of a once well-to-do lawyer trying to face up to the hardships of the Great Depression. Norris' letters reveal a certain bitterness about his financial difficulties but also an unfailing wit that he used against businesses that he used against businesses that he believed were trying to cheat him, particularly the exchange of letters and "legal briefs" between Norris and the Consolidated Gas, Electric Light and Power Company. Six folders of bills and receipts, arranged chronologically by decade, follow the business correspondence.
The third sub-division consists of Norris' legal and political correspondence which is arranged chronologically and within the respective folders.
Fourthly, miscellaneous items of Norris are arranged topically, from a folder of newspaper clippings, to miscellaneous pamphlets to unaddressed postcards.
The third major section of the Norris family papers consists of the correspondence of members of J. D. Norris' immediate family (minus their correspondence with J. D. Norris). Again, these have been arranged genealogically as follows: that of Mrs. William M. and Susan F. Norris; that of William Catesby Norris; that of Sarita M. and Susan F. Norris; that of Cabell Norris; and that of Josephine, and Martha Jefferson Norris. The significant portion of this section are the letters Ellen Norris wrote to her parents from Richmond apparantly during Grant's siege. The papers of other Norris' have been placed chronologically following the regular Norris family correspondence. The family papers also include various cloth items, notebooks and photographs. Of particular interest is the undated civil war material.
Related family papers consist of a few letters, 1861-1875, of George Gardner Hobson and his wife Sarah and several letters, 1863-1920, of the Della Torre family. Particularly interesting among the latter are the letters from Frank Della Torre to his mother Mrs. P. Della Torre written during the 1870s while Frank was a student at the University of Virginia. These two family collections are arranged chronologically.
Also included in th eother family papers are eighteenth and nineteenth century legal documents of the Arnold Smith and Whipple families. These are broken down by family, chronologically by decade within the family division.
Contents List
- Letters by Col. William Norris 1862-1864 (Box 1)
- "Confidental Circular" by Col. William Norris 1865 Mar 16 (Box 1)
- Jefferson Davis to Col. William Norris 1880 Feb 20, ALS (Box 1)
- Letters to Col. William Norris 1857-1896 (Box 1)
- Letters and scraps of paper of William Norris n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Col. William Norris 1890-1894 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1880-1889 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1890-1900 (Box 1)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and William Catesby Norris 1887-1890 (Box 1)
  chiefly re: U.Va. experiences
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris 1890-1899 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris 1900-1909 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris 1910-1919 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris 1920-1929 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris 1932 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Sarita M. Norris n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Susan F. Norris 1887-1920 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. J. D. (Cabell) Norris 1905-1909 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. J. D. (Cabell) Norris 1910-1919 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. J. D. (Cabell) Norris 1920-1930 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Mrs. J. D. (Cabell) Norris n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Josephine Norris n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence: J. D. Norris and Martha Jefferson "Bee" Norris n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous personal correspondence of J. D. Norris 1880-1940 and n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris 1899-1929 (Box 2)
- Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris as Secretary of the Mount Royal Improvement Association 1929-1934 (Box 2)
- Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris re Estate of Susan F. Norris 1935-1939 (Box 2)
- Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris and Dr. Henry Russell re repayment of a loan Norris had made to Russell 1935-1940 (Box 2)
- Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris and John B. Minor 1936 (Box 2)
- Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris and Consolidated Gas, Electric Light and Power Company 1937 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris 1930-1939 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Business Correspondence of J. D. Norris 1940-1941 and n.d. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous bills and receipts of J. D. Norris 1900-1943 and n.d. (Box 3)
- Legal papers of J. D. Norris 1899 (Box 3)
- Legal correspondence of J. D. Norris 1930-1939 and n.d. (Box 3)
- Political correspondence of J. D. Norris 1934-1940 (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings of J. D. Norris n.d. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets of J. D. Norris n.d. (Box 3)
- Postcards and Etchings of J. D. Norris n.d. (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1860-1889 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1890-1988 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1890-1899 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Mrs. William (Ellen) Norris 1900-1910 and n.d. (Box 5)
  (including fragments of letters)
- Correspondence of William Catesby Norris 1886-1899 (Box 5)
  (including eight compositions he wrote at Episcopal High School in 1886)
- Correspondence and notebooks of William Catesby Norris n.d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Sarita M. Norris 1880-1889 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Sarita M. Norris 1890-1919 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of Sarita M. Norris 1920-1929 (Box 7)
- Correspondence of Sarita M. Norris 1930-1932 (Box 8)
- Sarita M. Norris: Cancelled Checks 1903-1928 (Box 8)
- Correspondence of Sarita M. Norris n.d. (Box 8)
- Correspondence of Susan F. Norris 1900-1919 (Box 9)
- Correspondence of Susan F. Norris 1920-1922 (Box 10)
- Letters to "Miss Norris" or to "S. Norris" 1880 (Box 10)
  (unspecified)
- Letters to "Miss Norris" or "Miss S. Norris" n.d. (Box 10)
- Correspondence of Mrs. J. D. (Cabell) Norris 1897-1940 and n.d. (Box 10)
- Letters to Cabell Norris from her daughter, Josephine Norris 1920-1929 (Box 10)
- Letters to Cabell Norris from her daughter, Martha J. "Bee" Norris 1920-1930 (Box 11)
- Correspondence of Josephine Norris 1920-1929 (Box 11)
- Correspondence of Martha Jefferson "Bee" Norris 1925-1929 (Box 11)
- Correspondence of "Other" Norrises 1859-1904 (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous non-Norris correspondence and correspondence of unidentified individuals n.d. (Box 12)
- Letter fragments n.d. (Box 12)
- Report of Union dispatches re Lee's retreat toward Richmond [1863-1864?] (Box 12)
- Norris Family: Unidentified drafts of Memorial Addresses n.d. (Box 12)
- Norris Family: Post cards, unaddressed (Box 12)
- Norris Family: Photographs and Negatives (Box 12)
- Norris Family: Cloth Items (Box 13)
- Norris Family: Greeting Cards (Box 13)
- Norris Family: Notebooks (Box 13)
- Directions for the use of the "Valaze Massage Apparatus" n.d. (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Notes, Poetry, Prayers, etc. copied n.d. (Box 13)
- Unidentified scraps n.d. (Box 13)
- Correspondence of George and Sarah Hobson 1861-1875 (Box 14)
- Journal, apparantly written by a member of the Della Torre family, re his sudden illness while in the Confederate Army [1863-1864?] (Box 14)
- Della Torre Family correspondence: receipts 1865-1866 (Box 14)
- Della Torre family correspondence: including several letters to Mrs. P. Della Torre from Frank Della Torre, student at U. Va. 1870-1879 (Box 14)
- Della Torre Family correspondence: mostly receipts 1880-1881 (Box 14)
- Della Torre Family correspondence: receipts 1902-1920 (Box 14)
- Della Torre correspondence n.d. (Box 14)
- One page of the minutes of the Sessions of the Quarterly Court, Providence, R.I. 1661-1672 (Box 14)
- One page of what appears to be a Tanner's account book n.d. (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous Documents 1710-1857 (Box 14)
- Arnold Family Legal Documents 1729-1860 (Box 14)
- Nine letters to Benjamin Smith and two letters of later Smiths 1729-1746, 1882, 1889 (Box 14)
- Smith Family Legal Documents 1801-1846 (Box 14)
- Whipple Family 1760-1869 and n.d. (Box 15)
- Arnold, Smith and Whipple Family legal documents